[Music]
Stanford
University
okay all right so I I figured I have to
start with a review because I do
understand it's been two quarters since
uh since you last had lectures for me on
quantum mechanics on the other hand they
can't spend the whole quarter doing
that what I want to spend the quarter
on
is the applications of quantum mechanics
not the technology but the physics
problems and the basic physics problems
that I want to go through this quarter
are those for which quantum mechanics
were origin was originally uh invented
discovered
invented um
by Einstein Heisenberg G POI all those
people namely
atoms
electrons I'm going to do atoms first
you say how can I do atoms first before
I do electrons electrons are a part of
atoms it's all right we'll uh we'll do a
little bit about electrons just almost
nothing but just enough to be able to
write down the basic equations of the
hydrogen atom discuss the hydrogen atom
a little bit and then move on to further
investigations of the
electron and once and when we say the
electron was actually studying a class
of particles not just electrons a wide
class of particles which behave like
electrons which include me particles
quirks other things like that and then
the photon so it's going to be atoms
electrons and
photons but one of the themes that will
recur
is
symmetries symmetries of Nature and how
symmetries are realized in quantum
mechanics how symmetries are represented
in quantum mechanics and what they tell
us about the quantum mechanical system
symmetries in quantum mechanics are an
extremely powerful tool which I'm going
to tell you what a symmetry is if you
don't know what a symmetry is it's okay
at the moment but let's begin with a
very very lightning
review of the last quarter of quantum
mechanics first of all the whole story
Begins by asking how do you represent
the state of a system we could go back a
step and ask what is a system but I'll
assume you know what a system is and how
do you represent the states of a
system in classical mechanics the states
of a system are represented as points in
Phase space in quantum mechanics they're
represented by state vectors
the idea of a vector is not a vector
like a pointer in space pointing in a
certain direction in space it's an
abstract notion you can add vectors you
can multiply them by constants and the
mathematical structure of a state Vector
is a
mathematical Vector in a vector space
the vector space is not
three-dimensional except in special
cases it could be any dimensional so we
represent
States
by state vectors and the symbol for a
state
Vector is
D's K symbol K ke T which is the latter
half of the term bracket like braet or
braet every state can be either
represented by a k vector or by a
corresponding bra
Vector together we often put them
together to form a braet or a
bracket
um the bra vectors are in onetoone
correspondence with the c vectors and
you should really think of them roughly
as being the complex
conjugates in the same sense as complex
conjugates of complex numbers uh complex
numbers are ubiquitous in quantum
mechanics and so are complex vectors so
State vectors are represented by or
States states are represented by state
vectors the state vectors well we could
say a little bit more but uh if I were
to say the whole thing of course we
would then go through the entire quarter
so I won't in addition there are
observables things that you measure
measurables or
observables In classical mechanics there
are also observables they're the things
you measure but we don't spend a lot of
time talking about their mathematical
structure
we just assume you know what I'm talking
about when I say position of a particle
is measurable or momentum of a particle
or the energy of a particle or whatever
in quantum mechanics we have to be very
precise what we mean by an
observable and observables are
represented by linear Herm Mission
operators are label them with what are
these let's see these are Greek letters
what kind of letters are are the
English Roman Latin I don't
know by Latin
H yeah it's true it's Capital
Alpha okay but uh Latin letters are
representing observables and they are
Herm missan operators that act on the
vectors Herm mission for our purposes
translates or is the quantum mechanical
equivalent of real real as in real or
complex or
imaginary uh they are the real operators
which are equal to their own Herm
Mission
conjugate every such operator in the
space of states is called an observable
and presumably there is really a way to
to observe
it the igen values and igen vectors of
these Herm Mission operators play a
special role so let me just remind you
what is an igen value and an igen Vector
if you have a Herm Mission
operator you can
search for
vectors let's label the
vector let's label it little
A or B better yet Alpha since we want to
label it with a Greek
index let's label it with an
alpha and a being an operator can act on
Alpha and Alpha is an igen Vector of a
if the action of a is just to
multiply the vector Alpha by a number in
this case I'm use a redundant notation
the same notation for the igen value and
the igen vector and this says that the
igen value the igen vector Alpha is an
igen Vector of a with igen value Alpha
and the significance of that equation is
that first of all the set of igen values
of an operator or of an observable are
the set of possible results of
measurement if you have a quantity which
when you measure it can take on the
value 1 3 and 7even then the igen values
of that operator are 1 3 and 7 and so
forth the igen vectors are the state
vectors of the
system for which if you make a
measurement the answer is definite not
statistical determined deterministic and
the answer to the measurement is Alpha
okay so I assume we all remember this
I'm doing this mostly to just refresh
your
memory
okay now the particular systems we're
going to be discussing mostly in this
quarter are systems of particles
particles are largely characterized by
saying the things which have a location
in space an ordinary location in space
for example a space is onedimensional
then a particle is a thing which has a
coordinate X it's located somewhere As
an X if it's space is three-dimensional
then particles move around they have X Y
and Z and so forth
let's write formulas for the case of one
dimension but I'll tell you what to do
for three dimensions in a moment okay oh
sorry let's come back one one point that
I I need to emphasize for every bra and
every
cat let's
call the bra let's call it fi it is not
necessarily the particular bra that goes
together with Sai with the K Sai for
every par like that there is an inner
product there is a number that number is
in general a complex number and it is
represented as the inner product inner
product and it's a number it's a number
for every pair of
vectors uh it
represents a kind of product of the two
vectors it's similar in its mathematical
structure to the dotproduct between two
vectors in ordinary space but it's a
it's a more abstract object it's the
inner product between two vectors and it
plays an important role in the logic of
quantum mechanics in
particular if two states are
distinguishable uniquely by the property
that there's some observable that you
could measure which would be different
in the two of them let's suppose there's
some quantity that you could
measure and it
is
definite that the
answer in the state Sai is different
than the state fi then no then we would
say those two states are distinctly
different there's no chance of confusing
them there's a measurement you could do
to distinguish them then those states
are said to be orthogonal orthogonal
means physically identifiably
different and
mathematically it's the statement that
the two vectors have inner product equal
to
zero so orthogonality is a fundamental
property of relationships between
vectors which says that they are
different you can't confuse them well
you can confuse them but you shouldn't
confuse
them
okay now when it comes to particles the
most important observable is the
position of a particle and so let's just
discuss particles moving on a
line a line is the x-
axis the location of the particle is
just a value of x and obviously X should
be thought of as an
observable okay in particular there are
states which are labeled by a a value of
position let's call it
xn this is the point x not over here I'm
just using the KN here to indicate a
particular
position there are
states uh which are labeled by X which
have the property that if you measure
the particle the particle's position you
will definitely find it at X
knot
okay
good the next
concept oh and of
course State vectors for different
values let's call them x and x
Prime if x and x Prime are two different
positions
x and x
Prime then clearly those two states are
distinguishable operationally and by
measurement they're distinguishable so
these two states are
orthogonal now take any state any state
whatever of this particle call it
s it's inner
product with the state representing the
particle at X is called the wave
function the wave function of the
particle and it's written as s of X it's
the s that goes into the Schrodinger
equation it's Schrodinger S I believe
the Schrodinger was the first one to uh
to call it
SII
PSI and the
meaning of the wave function is closely
related to but not the same as the
probability that the particle is at
position
x s of X is an arbitrary function well
it's not completely arbitrary but let's
say it's some
function what does it represent s of x s
of X is closely related to the
probability to find the particle at
position X but it's not quite that the
probability itself let's call it P of
x
is the product of the wave function
times its complex conjugate the wave
function times its complex conjugate is
positive any number any complex number
times its own conjugate is always
positive probabilities are always
positive s of x's are generally complex
numbers they can be positive they can be
negative they can be imaginary they can
be uh whatever you
like so it would not make sense to say
that P is a probability but it does make
sense to say p times P star is a
probability good all right that's the
most important uh property of a particle
that it has a
position it has igen vectors which
represent particles of known
position and uh we can construct of
course a position operator a position
Operator just multiplies s of X by X
Itself by X all right so that's that's
the idea of position the other important
observable for a particle there are many
OB of course there are many observables
for a particle but the other
particularly important one is called the
what the
momentum the momentum In classical
mechanics and in quantum mechanics
positions and momenta come together oh
before we do that I should I should
discuss the uh the issue of a particle
moving not just in one dimension what
happens if a particle is moving in three
dimensions in other words like a real
particle then it has three observable
positions the three components of its
position namely X Y and Z if you like
but since you can rotate
axes uh you can just think of the
position as a point in three diens
dimensional space in that case we would
just think of X here as a point in
threedimensional
space we could fill it out we could fill
out the equations by saying there are
states which represent particles at
known locations in three dimensions X Y
and
Z this represents a particle located at
a point in threedimensional Space over
here X Y and Z and the rules would be
similar very similar uh the inner
products of X Prime y Prime Z
Prime that would be
zero if there's any
mismatch not if X is not equal to X
Prime and Y is not equal to Y but if the
entire Point XYZ is not the same as the
point x Prime y Prime Z Prime then these
are observably different positions for
particle and the states are orthogonal
to each
other I'm not I'm going to suppress the
Y and Z but keep in mind
that the position of a particle depends
on the dimensionality of the space that
we're talking about and in the real
world space is
three-dimensional okay for each
component of position there is also a
component of
momentum In classical physics for
non-relativistic classical physics the
momentum is just the mass times that
component of the
Velocity in quantum mechanics the
momentum is also unobservable and is
also represented by an operator by a
Herm Mission
operator Herm Mission operators can be
thought of in the abstract as objects
which act on mathematical vectors the
space of States on they can be thought
of more concretely as operations on Wave
functions either one you can think of
them concretely as operations that uh
that you what's what what about X itself
what is the
operation that represents the operator X
well it's just taking the state Vector s
of X so taking the wave function and
multiplying it by X if s of
X is a
function
representing the amp the probability
amplitude s of X is called the
probability amplitude or the wave
function of a particle then if you want
to apply the operator representing
position to S of X you just multiply s
of X by X that's
all uh the igen vectors of X are the
wave functions which are highly peaked
very very narrow direct Delta functions
all right in the same way the momentum
operator now I'm not going to explain
this in detail for this you go back to
the lecture notes to or or to the
lectures
themselves what lecture was it that we
talked about the momentum anybody
remember
art uh several of them but I think
around eight around eight May yeah yeah
yeah eight eight eight was uh eight was
uh that's right I remember with great
grief uh lecture eight right okay so the
momentum of a particle is represented by
an operator called
p and
p also does something to S of
X what it does to S of X is it
differentiates it it differentiates it
with respect to X but not
quite the real thing is that it
multiplies it by minus
I the complex number I there's a factor
of plun
constant H bar and then it
differentiates s d by
DX s of
X that is the operator
that acts on Wave functions that
represents the uh the observable
momentum everybody remember this yeah it
was a we went through it okay now what
about the igen vectors of momentum the
igen vectors of position are direct
Delta functions they are functions which
are zero
everywhere's
except at the igen value
position in other words the igen vector
representing a particle known to be at
xnot is a function which is zero
everywhere except at X knot where it's
very high and very narrow let's not
worry about its precise mathematical
definition it's called a der Delta
function what a and it's not too hard to
believe that if the wave function of a
particle is so concentrated at a
particular point that the probability
for finding it is zero everywhere as
except at that point that of course
makes
sense now what are the states for which
the momentum is certain in other words
what wave functions correspond to to
particles with definite momentum and
those are gotten by solving the igen
value equation the igen value equation
is that P whatever it is and in fact we
know what it
is well let's write the form let's let's
write the um the abstract equation first
that P on
S is equal to Little P
KN Time s the igen value being Little P
not Little P not is the value of
momentum that this particle has and in
this particular
State the uh the momentum of the
particle is known to be p this equation
translates just replacing P by minus i d
by DX minus
i d s by
DX is equal the P not the number a
numerical number times s of x s is a
function of x s of
X and this is easy to solve this is one
of these equations which says that the
derivative of something is proportional
to that same thing derivative of s apart
from a numerical number the numerical
number we could get we could mult get
rid of the IH bar on this side it would
reappear on this side uh this is the
equation of the type that represents an
exponential the derivative of something
is proportional to the something itself
and the solution of it is e to the
i p x ided PL plks
constant now I often get very tired of
writing plunks constant and I often just
set it equal to one we'll sometimes do
that in fact from uh I I'll try to track
it for the time being but later on I may
just drop it and uh I think by the time
I do drop it I will have done it enough
times that you'll know where the right
uh the right place where where it go
question yeah in the two equations you
just wrote there the the upper one with
the with the cats that would say that
those are or that's say igen Vector yeah
that says that igen Vector that that s
is an igen Vector of p with igen value P
but the one below holds for any wave
function any you think any wave function
is e to the Ia PS no no no but the
equation before forun no most wave
functions don't satisfy this equation oh
in
fact it's true for basically this wave
function okay now you'll notice of
course that there's a huge difference
between the igen vectors of position
which are these narrow little spiky
functions and the igen vectors of
momentum in
particular let's take the probability
that's associated with e to the
IX that's multiply it by its own complex
conjugate what happens if you multiply
this by its own complex
conjugate you get
one e to the I something * e to Theus I
something is just plain one so this wave
function the one which represents a
particle at with a definite momentum its
probability distribution is smeared out
over the entire
line by complete contrast the igen
vector of a particle located at a
definite position is highly concentrated
infinitely narrow and this of course is
a manifestation of the uh of the
uncertainty
principle uh if you know well if you
know the momentum of a
particle then its position is completely
uncertain and likewise if you know the
position of a particle its momentum is
also completely uncertain I'll refer you
back to the lecture notes uh to for that
purpose that's basically quantum
mechanics in a
nutshell question please I'm a little
bit confused I thought you said this we
know it's P0 so it's known yeah the
momentum is known the momentum is known
momentum but then when you try to
calculate the probability of this no no
the probabil the probability for
position what given that the momentum is
P now an experiment is going to do an
experiment not to check its momentum but
it's going to do an experiment which
measures its position two different
kinds of
experiments and that was 5 ofx five ofx
is the the the probability uh amplitude
for position that's right that's right
if the argument that's right that's
correct now there is also a notion of an
amplitude for finding different momenta
and I'll just remind you that's
connected to Foria transforms of s of X
but I'm not going to do that now if we
need Foria transforms we'll come back to
it at the
moment uh Foria transforms and the
momentum representation this is called
the position
representation the representation of
State vectors by S of x's is called the
position representation there is also a
momentum representation but I I it will
take us to a far field right now
question yes um what is the uh
probability of the position so in Star s
of x if the the the side function the
wave function is the is direct Delta
function and what is it when you
multiply that you know when you get into
probability what does that look like it
looks like the square of a Delta
function which is just higher than the
Delta function but it's concentrated at
the origin it's concentrated at the
origin and uh we have not talked about
normalizing wave functions making the
area under here equal to one that's a
thing that we want to do and uh but but
uh as I said I I hesitate to go into any
given thing too deeply because we'll
wind up doing the whole class again yeah
um so these State vectors are all
represented by column vectors is that it
you can you can represent them by column
vectors in other words but be a little
awkward to represent s of X by a column
Vector X takes on a continuous Infinity
of of values whereas the column Vector
is useful for a quantity which takes on
some discrete set of values so you can
think of it um formally in your head as
some kind of continuous column Vector
that's for the that's for the K vectors
and the bra vectors you can think of as
row vectors
okay but uh let's when we need that I'll
I'll remind you by then you will have
gone back and studied the the election
notes and you won't need
it
okay next thing how do things change
with time things do change with
time and the evolution of a system with
time is a special case of
Transformations that you can do on the
state of a system that of course is also
true in classical mechanics
the uh the motion of a system is
represented as a transformation in Phase
Bas a transformation of the phase Bas
position in quantum
mechanics the evolution of a system is a
special case of a
transformation that you can do on the
space of States taking every state to
some other
state and of course the um the idea
is
very straightforward if the state at one
instant of time is some sigh at some
later instant of time it is something
else and that something else is a
transform or a transformation of the
original
sigh there are some rules in quantum
mechanics about the nature of that
transformation oh that transformation
depends on the amount of elapsed
time okay if the amount of elapsed time
is very very short
then you would expect this
transformation to practically be the
identity Trans in fact let's go back if
the amount of time that's elapsed is
zero then of course the transformation
is completely trivial it just gives back
the same state you can say in that case
that the transformation was just the
identity operation on the uh on the
state Vector but more generally the time
evolution is characterized or the time
Evolution operation let's now call it
operator it is an operator in uh in the
sense of operators it's an operator but
it's an operator which depends on the
amount of elapsed time so let's give it
a name it's usually called
u u stands for unary but we'll come back
a moment for what unitary means uh and
it's parameterized by an amount of
elapsed
time and it's such that when it acts on
a state at a given instant of
time it takes you to the state at an
amount of time T later so for example if
it acts on the state whatever the state
happens to be at time T equals
z then it will give give you s at time
T it just updates the
state if it acts
on some state which happens to represent
things not at Time Zero but let's say at
time
T1 then it takes you to the state at
T1 plus t
in other words it represents the
evolution of the system from T1 to T1 +
T that's the notion of you that's the
notion of a uh time Evolution operator
it's a linear operator but is not a Herm
Mission operator what kind of operator
is it well now we need a postulate and
the postulate
is we can say the postulate very easily
it goes back to this minus first law of
physics that I harp on all the time that
information is conserved in quantum
mechanics what it means is that if you
start with two vectors two states which
are observably
different which cannot be confused in
other words which are
orthogonal and you let both of them
evolve they will stay orthogonal it will
not happen that two states that
are
observably different will evolve into
into states which are not observably
different all right so what that says is
that orthogonal vectors remain
orthogonal in fact you can do a little
bit better you can prove from that
statement that the inner product between
vectors is um unchanged by time okay so
let me just explore that idea a little
bit whatever U is it preserves the
relationships between Pairs of vectors
so for example if we start with
s and fi two vectors they may be
orthogonal or they may not be orthogonal
if they're orthogonal this inner product
is zero if they're not orthogonal it is
whatever it
is okay then the postulate is
that if we transform
s and we transform
fi now fi is a bra
vector and it transforms with the
hermiss conjugate of U that would be U
dagger what this equation
says is that the transform of SII when
you take its inner product with the
transform of fi is the same as the inner
product of SII with Fi in the beginning
it says that the inner products between
vectors don't change with
time
okay that can only be true for arbitrary
pair of s and thi if UD dagger time U is
the unit operator and that's called a
unitary operator UD dagger times U is
the unit operator or the identity
operator or just
one that's the notion of a unitary
operator and the time evolution in fact
all
transformations all interesting
Transformations that you do on the space
of states and we're going to talk about
others besides time Evolution all
interesting Transformations ways of
transforming vectors into other vectors
are
unitary UD dagger U is equal to one
that's different than saying you is
equal to one of course you was a unitary
operator all right let's uh let's pursue
it yeah question yeah the way you first
said it is if SII and fi were orthogonal
they would remain orthogonal but this is
a stronger statement than that this is a
actually it's not you can prove that if
you is a linear operator and it
maintains orthogonality then you can
prove that it maintains all inner
products but this says the time
evolution of a two state or two two
systems of different states don't even
if they're not orthogonal the the
overlap is conserved or whatever that's
right that's right and and I said that's
that's what you're saying is correct um
but I would say it follows from the if
orthogonality is preserved with time
then it's possible to prove that inner
products are preserved with time that's
a little exercise first of all think
about it in just ordinary
three-dimensional space supposing you
have some operation on vectors ordinary
vectors which preserves orthogonality
okay what kind of operations operators
on pairs of vectors will preserve the
fact that they're
orthogonal rotations right rotations
also have the property that they
preserve the inner products or the dot
products it's the same mathematics it's
the same mathematics so this is the
definition of a unitary operator there
any unitary
operators
uh so there are many possible things
could that could represent the evolution
of a system but they're all
unitary okay let's excuse me what would
be an example of non-unitary
transformation oh our mission operators
are usually not unitary except the
momentum is not a unitary operator the
position is not a unitary
operator uh
okay unitary operators are operators
whose igen values are phases everybody
know what a phase means an e to the I
times a real number a point on the unit
circle a phase represents on the complex
plane a point on the unit
circle one is a point on the unit circle
I is a point on the unit circle minus1
and minus I uh 1 over the < TK of 2 * 1
+ I is a uh is a
phase the unitary operators are the
analoges for operators of
phases their igen values are All Phases
so if I have a unitary operator and I
look at its igen values they will be
points sprinkled around on the unit
circle that's why they're called unitary
because in some sense they're link or
their the magnitude of their igen values
is
unit okay now
let's let's see what more we can learn
about you from making some reasonable
assumptions the first reasonable
assumption is that if T is equal to
zero then U is just equal to one all it
says is that if you don't allow any time
to elapse
the vector just comes back to itself and
U is equal to the unit operator so U of
Zer is equal to I the identity operator
the operator whose Matrix representation
is just one one along the diagonals it's
just the operator which does nothing it
just takes the thing back to itself now
is U unitary sure it is the Herm Mission
conjugate of U
is the Herm Mission conjugate of the
identity operator which is just the
identity operator
itself and identity time identity is
just identity so yes one is one or the
unit operator is unitary and it's it's
the time Evolution when no Evolution
happens okay what about evolution by a
very very small amount of time okay so
let's instead of writing U of zero let's
write U U of
Epsilon take U of Epsilon it is not one
something happens over time Evolution
but it is close to
one it's close to
one that of course is an assumption
that's the assumption that systems
evolve
continuously that they don't make
radical jumps over very very short
periods of
time uh and it is an assumption it's an
assumption ultimately which is justified
by experiment all right so that says
that U of A small time Epsilon if we
were to expand it in small in small
Epsilon would be 1 plus something
proportional to
Epsilon times an operator which is a
finite uh operator the smallness of
Epsilon is represented by Epsilon here
times
something which I'll temporarily call H
but it's a wrong identification in a
minute we're going to change
it
okay let me not call it
h what's another letter give me another
letter quick quick FG no no no no no g g
g fgh h yeah g good all right so U is of
this form there's nothing wrong with
this this is a correct
thing the only question is what do we
know about G so let's write down U
conjugate permission conjugate of
Epsilon that's equal to 1 plus Epsilon *
G conjugate the Herm Mission conjugate
of G and now let's multiply these
together and insist that the answer to
Leading order in epsilon is just one
okay so that will say that 1 + Epsilon G
dagga * 1 + Epsilon
G is equal to
1 looks a little queer 1 * 1 is
1 so what's left over what's left over
is
Epsilon times G dagger plus G and that
must be
zero to order Epsilon working to order
Epsilon the condition that U is unitary
is the condition that G Plus its own
Herm missan conjugate is equal to zero
in other
words getting rid of the
Epsilon that the conjugate of G is equal
to minus G
itself operators with this peculiar
property do you know numbers that have
that property you know any number that
has the property that it's minus its own
complex
conjugate IM it is true but there's a
wider class of them pure imaginary
things so this is the analog of G being
pure
imaginary if we multiply it by I it
becomes Herm Mission this is called
anti-mission Herm mission is when G
dagger equals g did we write that
someplace yeah a equal a dagger is an
observable G dagger equals minus G we
can fix that very simply just Define G
dagger to be now do I want plus or minus
I always forget
um it always takes me a minute or two
to
um I want to
write 1 + I Epsilon
H but I think the right answer is
minus that's that's a um
whether you put a plus sign or a minus
sign here is a convention complete
convention it defines
H this one becomes 1 + I Epsilon
H H
dager and the
condition just becomes that H equals H
dagger in other words if I put
a minus I
Epsilon h no plus I Epsilon H dagger
minus I Epsilon
H then the condition that U is unitary
is just the condition that H is Herm
mission in other words that H is an
observable yeah um what assumption are
we making that allows us to ignore the
Epsilon squ term we're just working to
order Epsilon we could work to order
Epsilon squ
but then we would have to be consistent
about it and put an Epsilon squar term
in here the Epsilon squar term that we
would want to put in here would be minus
Epsilon 2 / 2 *
h^2 and uh but we consistently work to
one power in epsilon and assume that
Epsilon is small enough that we can
ignore Epsilon squar we can do that
consistently we've done it over and over
and
over uh but then you're perfectly right
we do have to come back and check that
the formulas make sense to higher order
and they do I'll I'll I'll discuss that
a little bit but working systematically
to order Epsilon and dropping anything
of higher order than Epsilon I I just
wondered if what we if we were
following the details we have to say
that H is approximately or something
like that yes no well okay with this
definition you would say h is
approximately her Mission but um
allowing notice that Epsilon factors out
of both sides of this equation so once
it's factored out it just says that h no
I think the thing which is approximate
is this relationship here yeah and I'll
I'll come back and tell you what to do
uh if it
uh I'll tell you the right
formula in a little while at some point
okay so what do we learn we learn that
the that the unary time
Evolution which contains a U of
[Music]
T also is specified in terms of a
certain observable that I've called H H
stands for hamiltonian it also stands
for Herm Mission but it stands for
hamiltonian it is the hamiltonian of uh
of quantum
mechanics and so we come to the
conclusion that there exists an H we
will call call it the
hamiltonian and it is related to the
time Evolution for small time intervals
by 1 minus I Epsilon H what is the
general equation if Epsilon is not small
incidentally if Epsilon is not small we
might want to call it t we might give up
calling it Epsilon Epsilon is usually
reserved for a very small
quantity uh we might try writing U of T
but this wouldn't be right for large
times it wouldn't be large for for large
times Let's uh let's see if we can
improve it a little
bit well you know I think I won't spend
time at it I will just tell you the
answer the answer
is that this is really should be written
as e e to the
iht now why do I all let me uh let me
just um say a word or two about
exponentials if you have an
exponential e to some small number and
let's just call the small number Epsilon
where Epsilon is small times an ordinary
number and let me call the ordinary
number little
H Epsilon * h is a small number okay for
very small
Epsilon e to the Epsilon H is 1 plus
Epsilon H does everybody know that
that's the formal tailor series
expansion of keeping only the first
term assuming the second term and higher
terms are negligible okay now supposing
you want to take you want to make
Epsilon a little bigger
instead of just Epsilon I want to take e
to 2
Epsilon * h e to the 2 Epsilon * H is
just the square of e to the Epsilon
h e to 2 * something is just a square so
it's equal to 1 + Epsilon
H
squared supposing you do this over and
over and O which incidentally is equal
to
1 plus
2 Epsilon h plus Epsilon 2
h^2 right but this is still an
approximation this was an approximation
to this this is still an approximation
to
this here's a theorem that if you do
this over and over enough enough times
let's say n times e to the Epsilon * n *
H such that Epsilon * n is finite in
other words Epsilon * n Epsilon is an
infinitesimally small number but I do it
enough times so that n * Epsilon is a
finite number namely
T I do this over and
over what
happen
excuse me let me go
back let's do it this way 1+ Epsilon
H and I do this a number of times a
large number of times
in such that n * Epsilon equals T what
do I get anybody know a binomial
expansion it's a binomial it's a
binomial expansion but it's also
a construction of the exponential
function okay uh it's a rigorous theorem
that as Epsilon gets small and N gets
large in such a way that n * Epsilon is
kept fixed this just becomes e to the
HT say it
again
one person talk I think it's right I
think it's right right and the way you
can just understand it is by saying that
for small
Epsilon
um 1 + Epsilon H is the same as e to the
Epsilon H and if you take it to the nth
power the Epsilon just multiplies the n
and becomes
T okay so I will tell you right now the
general Iz a of this for finite
times one this should be a minus sign
here 1us
iht for finite T really becomes e to the
minus iht and this is an important fact
but for small intervals small
Epsilon we can just be consistent and
work to order Epsilon we'll find out uh
everything we need to know okay so
there's a concept now of a
hamiltonian let's see if we
can understand this equation a little
bit
better
um
let's take the wave function s or the
state Vector State Vector s at a time t+
Epsilon I'm starting at time t with a
certain wave function and I'm allowing
it to change over a tiny time interval
what is the answer to this the answer to
this is that it is equal to e to the i h
Epsilon times s at time T let's just see
what I
did minus or plus sorry minus minus
here that's starting at time T let's
update by a small little time Epsilon
the rule is we multiply by U of T but
sorry U of Epsilon we're updating by an
amount of time Epsilon and that's
equivalent to multiplying by e to the
minus i h Epsilon Time s of t so this is
the rule for going from a time to a
neighboring time but now let's write
that out as 1 minus i h
Epsilon Time s of
T and let's write this side I'm not
going to forget the
okay yeah okay yeah let's put them in
and this one here is s of t plus
Epsilon now let's multiply out 1 * s of
T is s of T but let's take that over to
the left hand side that'll give us s of
t plus Epsilon minus s of T just the
term coming from one the term coming
from one will give us the difference
between s of t plus
Epsilon minus s of
T you see where we're going we're
building a differential equation right
for s s of t + Epsilon minus s of T is
just equal to -
I Epsilon s of
T and finally divide by
Epsilon okay what's the left hand
side the left hand side is the time
derivative of the state Vector s
and the right hand side is just minus i
s of t Okay so that leads us finally to
the Schrodinger
equation the Schrodinger equation
says that d by I'm DCI by
DT this could be a wave function or it
could be the state Vector I will leave
the notation a little bit um abused I
won't bother writing the K Vector here
it stands for both the equation for the
state vector or the equation for the
wave function itself DCI by DT is
equal to minus i h
s if you want to put vectors in if you
want to turn it into a equation for a
state Vector you put
uh K notations there other wise it's
just the equation for a wave function
this is the Schrodinger equation this is
the the time dependent schro schinger
equation okay this is Schrodinger
equation time dependent the
TDS time dependent shinger equation and
what it tells you is how the state
Vector changes as a function of time if
you are so lucky to know what the
hamiltonian is is hamiltonian is a Herm
Mission operator and you can make all
kinds of quantum mechanical systems just
to play with by choosing different hes
we did this last
quarter okay
um what about the time independent
shring or equation the time independent
Shing equation is just the statement
that H is a Herm Mission operator it has
igen values it has igen vectors its igen
values are the observable
uh values that you would get if you
measured H and what are they called they
have another
name energy levels energy levels
incidentally I promised you that I would
keep around plunks constant and I've
already dropped
it
uh it goes over
here it goes over
there all right I don't promise by any
means that I will be consistent about
plunk constant yes I will be completely
consistent by choosing plunk constant to
always be equal to one sometimes I'll
put it in sometimes I won't put it in
but I will never confuse it with I or
the square root of
two okay so that's the time dependent
the time independent schinger equation
that's just the igen value equation for
the igen values of H and all it says is
that h
on an igen Vector of the energy a state
with definite
energy is equal to e time the
energy e being the IG value of
H E being the igen value of H so this
equation here is the equation which
tells you how to find the states and the
values of energy that go with them that
correspond to states of definite
energy you solve this equation and it
gives you a whole bunch of possible igen
values and igen vectors those are the
igen vectors and igen
values of the energy operator okay and
again we went through this we did some
examples last uh last two quarters ago
on the other hand this equation tells
you how the state Vector changes with
time and as you can see it's the same h
on both in both equations so the the
question of the energy levels of a
system are intimately bound up with the
way that the system changes with time
okay
so
good and that's uh that's quantum
mechanics in a uh I said before it was
quantum mechanics in a nutshell well
it's a slightly bigger nut but uh but
that's it that's that's what you need to
know that's a summary of uh a quarters
worth of quantum mechanics that we did
any
questions can you if if in the time
dependent
equation
independ
equation if in the time dependent Shing
equation you replace S with
e s with e yeah can you can you do yeah
then then you can drop the K
things
right then it becomes just an equ a
differential equation because H * e will
be just e *
e no no we don't want to drop the the
Cat symbol leave this leave the cat
symbol
there right leave the cat symbol there
for the moment what we can do is we can
ask how a igen vector changes with time
that we can do so we can plug in here
and we can ask how the igen vector
changes with time and the answer is that
the igen vector will change with time by
just multiplying it by I times the
energy level that's what tells us how
igen vectors change with time anybody
remember the answer how an igen Vector
changes with
time it just gets multiplied by e to the
I * the energy time time
okay so that uh we can go through that
we don't
need it's in the notes go back to it and
uh and check it out all right now the
time evolution is one example of
Transformations that you can do on a
system uh which preserve certain facts
about the system in particular which
preserve the inner products between uh
vectors in other words Words which
preserve The Logical relationships
between vectors preserve the notion of
orthogonality preserve the notion of
vectors being the same vectors and uh
and that kind of um
uh there are many other kinds of
Transformations that you may want to do
on a
system in particular among them are
symmetry
Transformations we will need to talk
about symmetry Transformations now I
will tell you where we're going one of
the most important symmetries of nature
that occur over and over and over again
in all sorts of contexts but in
particular in the theory of
atoms is rotational
symmetry
a atom in particular a hydrogen atom a
hydrogen atom is an electron moving in a
central force
field the equations of a hydrogen atom
are rot Ally symmetric and that's
because the potential energy the Kum
potential is rotationally symmetric it's
a central
force and so hydrogen atoms and
basically all systems in nature really
but hydrogen atoms in particular enjoy
rotational symmetry if you rotate all it
means is that if you rotate your
coordinates the description of the
hydrogen atom doesn't change or another
way to say it is if you rotate the
hydrogen atom at it's still a hydrogen
atom it may or not may not be the same
state but it's still a hydrogen atom
described by the same set of
equations
so the notion of a symmetry is Central
in quantum mechanics it is also in
classical mechanics but it uh comes up
and really hits you over the head in
quantum
mechanics and we need to
explore largely for the purposes of
understanding rotational symmetry we
need to understand the concept of a
symmetry so I'm going to spend 15
minutes explaining exactly what a
symmetry
is keep in mind if you want to keep one
in mind there are two that you can keep
in mind uh for uh just to have something
in your head one of them is rotation
symmetry where it just says that if you
take a system which satisfies a certain
set of equations and you rotate it
physically rotate it physically rotate
about an axis you may or may not change
it I can tell you this if you rotate me
you'll change me right yeah you will uh
if the Earth weren't here and I was in
outer space and free space then the uh
the lard equation whatever the equation
governing me is would be the same for
the rotated or the unrotated another way
of saying it is I couldn't tell whether
I was rotated or not if you're rotate me
and then just go away I can't tell that
I was rotated because the equations that
govern my metabolism my internal
structure and so forth are exactly the
same as had not rotate been
rotated okay so rotation symmetry is one
example another example is translation
symmetry if you take me in outter space
and you set me down and you say how do I
feel I feel fine you take the same state
but you translate me over by a meter and
you ask me how I feel I say exactly the
same as I felt
before it's a symmetry on the other hand
there are situations where translations
may not be a symmetry you know if there
was a uh furnace over there a fire hot
fire and you put me over here and you
said how do you feel I feel fine now
translate me over to here how do you
feel well I don't feel so fine okay so
the presence of an
object may break translation symmetry
on the other hand if you think about it
a minute wait a minute what if I really
translate everything me and the
furnace then we restore the translation
symmetry so symmetries are operations or
there are operations that you can do on
states of systems and if the operation
doesn't
change the equations doesn't change the
properties of the system doesn't change
the way you describe the system then
that transformation is called a
symmetry for a free particle for for any
ordinary system if it's out in out of
space far from anything else and you
translate it that's a symmetry you
rotate it that's a symmetry what if you
squeeze it change its Dimensions by
squeezing
it that's generally not a symmetry you
know if you take a crystal of rock salt
or something and you squeeze down on it
and compress it by a factor of two it's
doesn't behave the same
way uh so there are all kinds of things
which are not
symmetries nevertheless they still may
be operations that you can Define but
they may not be
symmetries okay let's uh let's talk
about the condition let's first of all
try to quantify that
idea we have
States
let's the generic or typical state of
the system that we're interested in is
called
Sai we're going to do an operation on it
that operation might correspond to
rotating the system it might correspond
to translating the system or it might
correspond to something uglier than that
like squeezing it or stretching it but
doing something to
it and let's represent
that
by an operator
V I use V because I've already used U
you but I intended to be a unitary
operator why a unitary operator well if
I really have a
symmetry and I have two states which are
different than each other I apply the
Symmetry operation I expect them to stay
different if there are two states of uh
of me happy me and sad me they're
different from each other they're
observably different there's a there's
an observ that you can measure the
happiness uh operator and the different
if you then rotate the
state out in outer space the distinction
should remain so that means that
orthogonal states should remain
orthogonal when you do a symmetry
operation and that says that the
operator V should be
unitary so V is unitary and it
represents V equal V dagger V = 1 I
don't use U because I'm saving you for
the special case of time translation of
evolution okay now let's suppose oh uh
yeah this is a little bit tricky so
we'll there's U's and there's v's and
it's it's it's quite tricky it takes me
half an hour each time I try to do do
this to get it right but it's also very
very simple okay let's
suppose that a wave function or a state
Vector I'll use them interchangeably
let's call it
S1 under time
Evolution
becomes S
2 if I take S1 and I allow it to evolve
with time let's represent that by
putting a little U here U represents
time
Evolution V does not V is something
else and if I take s 1 and allow it to
evolve for a certain amount of time it
will become S 2 okay so that's under U
another way to say that over here is
that U on S
1 is equal to S 2
that's all evolve s 1 for a little bit
of time and you get S
two okay now let's imagine the
transformed version of this transformed
it could be by rotation it could be by
translation by some
symmetry
operation what does this equation say
for the transformed things well let's
call this let's call this S
Prime now there are too many let's let's
keep in mind exactly what's going on
here one and two represent some initial
State and some final State Evolution
from one to another Prime and unprimed
represent the action of the Symmetry
operation which could be rotation could
be rotation or it could be
translation okay here's what I maintain
If there really is a symmetry then s 1
Prime
if we were talking about rotations then
s 1 Prime is just the rotated state of
S1 s 1 Prime will
evolve
to the rotated version of S
2 let's see what that says okay if I
evolve myself
over a period of time and I'm in some
State and I get some other state I go
from happy to not so
happy then when I rotate myself I should
also find under the same Evolution that
I go from the rotated Happy State to the
to the rotated Noto Happy State that's
what it really means to have a symmetry
that um that the evolution of the
transformed
State behaves the same way as the
original state it's a little bit tricky
okay let's see if we can make an
equation out of this
now
[Music]
um yeah okay so the first the first row
here is just the equation that S 2 is U
S
1 that's what this
says the second equation let's go to the
second equation to go from unprimed to
Prime you multiply by
V so the second equation here says that
V it says
that I'm sorry I this always confuses me
um ah it says that 2
Prime is equal to
U Time s 1
Prime to go from one to two is time
Evolution to go from unprimed to Prime
is V is the Symmetry operation all right
so s 1 Prime is V * s 1 right all right
so we have u v * I 2
is
U Time s 1 Prime and S 1 Prime is V * s
1 okay that's the rightand side the left
hand side is V on S 2 but S 2 is U * s
1 so
after per ual confusion that uh that uh
is uh stumps me every time I try to do
this on the
Blackboard what it says is that if a
thing is a symmetry in other words if it
preserves the way EV Evolution takes
place if it's a
transformation which preserves the time
relationships between vectors then it
says that V * U must be equal to U * V
this of course must be true for every
state if it's to be a true symmetry of
nature a true symmetry of nature
rotation symmetry for example is not
something which only applies if I'm
standing vertically
upright it should apply to any
particular state of the system and so if
V *
U on any S one is equal to U * V on any
s 1 what it says is that symmetries of
nature are such their operations their
V's unitary
operators which
commute with the time Evolution
operator for all for
all for
all yes in fact for all time it we'll
see it's enough let be true for one time
and it will be true for all time but yes
that's
correct okay so Unity AR
operations things you can do to the
state vectors which preserve
orthogonality which commute with the
time Evolution operator are
symmetries that preserve the evolution
uh The evolutionary
relationships so physically you're
saying you can rotate and then wait or
you can wait and then rotate exactly the
words are very simple and they make
perfect sense and uh
yes that's exactly what it
says okay so how do we identify
symmetries we look for operations which
commute with a Time Evolution
operator now remember that the time
Evolution
operator is
itself let's take the limit of a small
time Evolution just to analyze it a
little bit this says well first of all
yeah okay it says the V
Time 1 + I Epsilon
H 1 - I Epsilon H 1 - I Epsilon H is
equal to 1 - I Epsilon H this is the
first order again times
V I'm just expanding it out uh the first
order is good enough it gives us
everything we really want to
know first of all V * 1 is equal to 1 *
V so those
cancel and what it says is that minus I
Epsilon
VH
equals minus I Epsilon
HV or canceling out the minus I Epsilon
it says that V commutes with the
hamiltonian okay let's cancel out these
things the minus I
epsilons
a symmetry is a unitary operation which
commutes with the
hamiltonian any unitary operation which
commutes with the hamiltonian is a
symmetry and any symmetry is a unitary
operation which commutes with the
hamiltonian that's very
abstract that's extremely abstract and
in order to appreciate it we have to do
a couple of examples we'll do some
examples in a moment but let's just
focus on that that unary operations on
the space of states which commute with
the hamiltonian are symmetries what
liaran what's that what limited V to
being
unitary what limit sorry what limited
what required that V is
unitary oh yeah a symmetry whatever a
symmetry is it preserves logical
relationships between the
vectors so it's an assumption it's an
assumption that the symmetries of nature
take orthogonal states to orthogonal
States
okay that uh seems plausible a symmetry
should not take two states which are
distinctly different from each other and
act on them to give states which are not
distinctly different from each other you
wouldn't call that a symmetry you could
say mutually exclusive yeah mutually
exclusive things should stay mutually
exclusive right okay so we now have a
abstract mathematical
definition
uh of any symmetry operator of any
symmetry this will become much clearer
when we do some
examples
symmetry commutator of H with v
is equal to
zero that's what it
says do you remember from uh two
quarters ago what the commutator of a
thing with the hamiltonian
is the time derivative of
it yeah so what this says is that
whatever the operator V is it's
conserved conservation of a certain
quantity in this case
v meaning that it commutes with a
hamiltonian is the same as saying
there's a symmetry you've seen this
before In classical mechanics what's the
connection between symmetries and
conservation laws called In classical
mechanics it's called nerus
theorem right it's much simpler in
quantum mechanics it's much simpler in
quantum mechanics
uh we don't need any fancy lran or
anything else all we need to know is
that time Evolution commutes with the
Symmetry operation
itself and that can be read in two
different ways it can say that doing the
Symmetry
operation
um well it says what it says it can be
read two different ways but uh but they
both say the same thing okay so that's
now let's go one step further there are
different kinds of symmetries let me
give you some examples of two different
kinds of
symmetries there are discrete symmetries
and there are continuous
symmetries let me give you an example of
a discrete
symmetry
um think about reflection in a
mirror reflection in a mirror takes a
right hand to a left hand okay um that's
the mirror image of a left hand as a
right hand that's a discrete operation
it takes left to right but there's
nothing sort of in between it's just a
discrete operation left to right let me
give you another example of a discrete
operation
um let's suppose we have a pair of
electrons or a pair of particles a pair
of particles and they happen to be the
same the same kind of particle a pair of
electrons or a pair of
protons then if I take the two particles
and I interchange
them whatever the state is I interchange
one particle with the other particle
that's a symmetry why because the
particles are of exactly the same kind a
proton over here and a proton over here
is the same as a proton over here and a
proton over here that's just interchange
of them those are discrete
operations uh discrete operations means
that there's sort of nothing in between
or let's say heads and tails just say
heads and tails a head and a tail if the
coin happens to have no markings on it
whether it's heads or tails and you turn
it over then the physics of the coin and
flipped coin are exactly the same those
are discrete
operations by discret I mean in
distinction to continuous operations and
continuous operations are like rotation
in space rotation in space you can do a
very small rotation small means one by a
very small angle in fact you can go
further you can say that every rotation
about an axis can be built up by tiny
rotations about that same
axis that means that the rotations have
a continuity to them that the flip of a
coin does not have flip of a coin is
either its heads or its tails and
there's nothing in between for for
classical
coins
um for systems in three-dimensional
space you can or two-dimensional space
for that matter you can rotate them you
can rotate them by 90° that's a big
that's a transformation but you can
build up that 90 degree rotations by
lots and little lots of little infinite
tal transformation those are called
continuous symmetries what about
translation symmetry it's translation
symmetry continuous or discrete well
it's continuous you can take any
translation of a system and think think
of it as being compounded out of lots of
small
translations The Continuous symmetries
are the ones in particular the rotation
symmetries and translation symmetries
are the ones I want to focus
on okay what do we know about continuous
symmetries we know we can build them out
of lots of little Elementary small
Transformations so let's focus on the
small Transformations we're going
through
basically the same manipulations that we
went through over
here time translation is a continuous
thing you can build up a time
translation by 10 seconds by thinking of
it as lots of little time translations
by micros
seconds okay and that led us to the
conclusion that
use
are
related to to her Mission operators
through this relationship here exactly
the same is true of every continuous
symmetry exactly the same thing is true
every continuous
symmetry can be thought of as being
built up by little infinite tmal ones
which have the form 1 - I Epsilon not
times a hamiltonian but something some
Herm Mission operator let's call it
g g stands for
generator G stands for generator and
what we're thinking about now is a
symmetry transformation but one of them
which is very close to being the
identity such a
transformation can always be represented
as something close to the unit operator
and close to the unit operator means
just shifted by a small
amount by the same argument that told us
that H is Herm
Mission G is also her
Mission symmetry
operations which are continuous can be
represented in terms of infinitesimal
Transformations which are generated by a
generator
G and if we plug this into here and we
then write
that commutator of H with 1 - I Epsilon
G is equal to0 what does that
say what's the commutator of H with one
commutator anything with one is zero
everything commutes with a simple with
the oper the operator
zero the I Epsilon that factors out and
what it tells us is that um symmetry
operation
are generated by this is what it means
to be generated by generated by means
can be built up by lots of little
ones they're generated by things which
commute with the
hamiltonian so if you want to find all
of the symmetries of a problem you'll
start looking around for all the things
which commute with the
hamiltonian there's another feature of
things which commute with a hamiltonian
do you remember from last
quarter it's true both in the what was
that conserved they're
conserved so conservation and symmetry
are closely connected if you want to
find all of the symmetries of a problem
it's equivalent to finding all the
things which are
conserved all right now this was very
abstract and so we need to do an example
or two to get the
idea let's do an example and let's
[Music]
begin with
translation translation of a particle
from one place to
another okay translation of a wave
function we want to take a wave
function here's a wave function and
we're going to move it a little bit
we're going to translate
it to a new wave function and we want to
find out what operation does that if we
have a s of
X what operation do we do to translate
it to a new
position we're going to take that new
position to only deviate by a small
amount by amount Epsilon but we know
what the answer is the answer is s of X
goes
to S of x x +
Epsilon Epsilon now could be a large
number we're just translating by a large
number but in specifically I want to
think about the case of a small
translation translation by a little bit
okay
so s of X in other words we can write
that the translated wave
function in fact we can write it this
way whatever V is whatever V is we
haven't figured out V is yet but
whatever V is it acts on S of x to give
us s of X Plus
Epsilon that's pretty easy that's how
that's that's what a v is that's what
the V does in this case it acts on S of
X and it translates the wave function by
amount
Epsilon okay now if Epsilon is small we
can also write that this is equal to S
of
X plus the derivative of s I with
respect to
X time
Epsilon
so what V
does what V on S does is it gives back
the same S Plus something proportional
to the
derivative that suggest doesn't suggest
it proves that whatever V is is it's the
unit
operator that's the first term here it
acts on S of x to give back s of X plus
a small change and the small change is
Epsilon times the derivative
operation I haven't written on X we
could write on x v sorry Time s v is an
operator it's the unit operator plus
Epsilon time the derivative oper
operator we can act on any wave
function and what it will give us is the
wave function infinitesimally
displaced okay now what about DCI by DX
what about D by DX d by DX is an
operator it operates on Wave functions
it's a linear operator right it's
connected with the momentum
operator remember the relationship the
momentum operator P equal minus i d by
DX all right so what do we want to do we
want to write let's uh let's multiply by
I get rid of the I here and divide by
har differentiation is I over har time
momentum so let's write this that way 1
plus Epsilon I Epsilon over
HR times the
momentum we now have an example of a
infinite decimal symmetry operation by
infinite deal I mean just by a little
bit of a shift and we found out what its
generator is the
G where was it did we do we have G here
no yeah V is 1 - I Epsilon
G in this
case I would have much preferred that I
defined things so that this came out to
be minus here but
uh the momentum definition yeah F to the
right further to the right upper right
upper right yeah this one I think that's
right
Theus multip no no that's
right H you think this is wrong no it's
right right so let's see
so I substituted I think I got this
right wait wait sorry did
I yeah that's
right do you disagree with
this nothing think it's right all right
now
um
ah I think if I shift the wave function
to the right if I shift the wave
function to the right that's really
putting a minus sign
here
yeah yeah I made a mistake in defining a
shift to the right a
shift it looks like it should be X Plus
Epsilon but s of X goes to S of x minus
Epsilon so this is actually a minus sign
here if you track that through we will
find out that there's a um a minus sign
here
yeah okay so it identifies for us what
the Symmetry generator G is for
translations and what is it it's the
momentum divided by plunks
constant right momentum divided by plunk
constant we can write that the generator
of translations here's the language the
generators of the generator
of X
translation
is p subx p subx strictly speaking
divided by plunk
constant
uh we can drop the plunks constant I
will drop the plunks constant and as a
matter of fact the definition the
official definition really doesn't have
the plunks constant in it but
um there's an example there's an example
P of X now is p of X is the momentum
along the x axis
conserved depends on the
hamiltonian it depends on the
hamiltonian so let's write down a
hamiltonian the hamiltonian for free
particle a particle moving in empty
space with no forces acting on it
h in that case is just p^2 over 2 m the
momentum squar divided by twice the
mass if this is a one-dimensional
problem then it really is just PX just
the X component of momentum does The X
does the hamiltonian commute with PX
well that becomes equivalent to the
question of whether PX commutes with px^
squar yes every operator commutes with
every function of
itself P of X commutes with P of x^2 it
commutes with P of X cubed it commutes
with any function of P of X so for a
free particle moving along the x- axis
we first of all find that the momentum
is
conserved and of course we also have a
translation symmetry
the translation symmetry is just the
fact that the free particle will behave
the same way wherever you start it if
you start it here and it gets to here
then if you start change the starting
point it'll just everything will just
translate okay so that's that's an
example p is both a conserved quantity
and the generator of translations what
if there are more directions of space if
there are more directions of space then
there are several symmetries you can
translate along the xaxis you can
translate along the Y AIS you can
translate along the
z-axis in that case the hamiltonian
becomes px^ 2 + p y^ 2 over 2 M plus pz
^2 over 2
m and the translation symmetry along the
xaxis is still just
PX translation along the y- axis the
generator is py and so forth and each of
them commutes with a hamiltonian
so this is an example of the connection
between symmetries and conservation laws
which is very
simple the next time it looks like we're
about out of time the next time we will
do rotation
symmetry rotation symmetry is much it's
much more interesting it's much more
involved it uh and it will bring us to
the subject of group
Theory uh there's some group Theory here
but the group theory is completely
trivial the next time we will talk about
rotations in space and what's
interesting about rotations in space is
they don't commute with each other a
rotation about X followed by a rotation
by Y is not the same as a rotation by y
Rotation by X and that will give us the
idea of non-commuting
symmetries
symmetries collections of symmetries
which don't commute with each other and
when we find those they have power they
have real power to tell us about all
kinds of physical properties of a
system okay so next time rotation
symmetry for more please visit us at
stanford.edu